{"tossups": [{"question": "This man\u2019s fatal stabbing allegedly prompted his scheming wife Olympias to place a crown on the assassin\u2019s body. This man received the one word reply \u201cIf\u201d after issuing a series of threats to Sparta. After this man pacified Greece, he organized cities into the military League of Corinth. This ruler\u2019s introduction of the sarissa contributed to a great victory over Thebes at Chaeronea. For the point, name this Macedonian king, the father of Alexander the Great.", "answer": "<b> Philip of Macedon</b> (accept<b> Philip II</b>; prompt on Philip)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this dictator of Uganda.", "answer": "Idi<b> Amin</b> Dada", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In his later years, this man retreated to the House of the Deaf Man where he painted 14 murals that included the \u201cFight with Cudgels\u201d and a depiction of his alleged lover Leocadia. This artist created a painting of Joachim Murat\u2019s cavalry attacking civilians in his<em> Charge of the Mamelukes</em> and a series of 82 prints in the<em> Disasters of War</em> series. This artist\u2019s most famous work shows a white-shirted Spaniard before a French firing squad. For the point, name this Spanish painter of<em> The Third of May, 1808</em>.", "answer": "Francisco<b> Goya</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Orange trees transplanted to this island from Seville in the early 16th century failed in its dry soil, and the abandoned fruit evolved into the bitter lahara, whose peel is dried and used as an extract. Tula Rigaud led a 1795 slave revolt on this island, which is home to a Jewish community dating to the 1650\u2019s. A 1969 oil strike on this island devastated its capital of Willemstad. For the point, name this southern Caribbean island, an autonomous country within the Netherlands found east of Aruba.", "answer": "<b> Curacao</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This speech promises to \u201cbreak the bonds of mass misery\u201d for those who live in \u201chuts in villages,\u201d\u201cnot because we seek their votes, but because it is right.\u201d Part of this speech pledges to \u201csupport any friend\u201d and \u201coppose any foe\u201d to \u201csecure the survival of liberty.\u201d This speech, which was preceded by a Robert Frost reading, culminates with the advice \u201cask not what your country can do for you, ask what you can do for your country.\u201d For the point, name this speech given on January 20, 1961 by the first Catholic US president.", "answer": "John Fitzgerald<b> Kennedy</b>\u2019s<b> inaugural</b> address (or<b> JFK</b>\u2019s<b> inaugural</b> address; you do<em> not</em> need to prompt on Kennedy alone)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One side in this conflict set up the Terijoki [teri-yo-kee] government in a failed attempt to gain legitimacy. Simo Hayha accumulated 250 sniper kills in this conflict, cementing legendary status as the\u201cWhite Death.\u201d After failing to defend the Mannerheim Line, one side in this conflict was forced to give up Karelia and later sought vengeance in the Continuation War. For the point, name this 1939 to 1940 war between Finland and the Soviet Union.", "answer": "<b> Winter</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This battle began when the Ho-Chunk division attacked without orders. Commander Joseph Daviess was lost in a cavalry charge in this battle, whose victors were joined by the Yellow Jackets. This battle led to the burning of Prophetstown and the defeat of Tenskwatawa, the brother of Tecumseh. For the point, name this 1811 battle in Indiana that was used as a rallying cry in the presidential election of 1840 by William Henry Harrison.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Tippecanoe</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man, the only Republican member of the Keating Five, became Chair of the Senate Armed Services Committee in 2015. Push polls in South Carolina tanked this man\u2019s 2000 presidential primary campaign, and his later Presidential run fell apart after choosing Sarah Palin as his running mate. For the point, name this runner-up in the 2008 Presidential Election, an Arizona senator who died in 2018.", "answer": "John<b> McCain</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This man turned on his former ally, Rim Sin I, after the city of Larsa failed to aid this man in his fight against Elam. This member of the Amorite First Dynasty completed a campaign begun by his father Sin-Muballit. This man is depicted receiving instruction from Shamash at the top of a stele where 282 of his decrees were inscribed. Under this man\u2019s rule, punishments were based on the idea of \u201can eye for an eye.\u201d For the point, name this Babylonian king known for his law code.", "answer": "<b> Hammurabi</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "Before this man\u2019s fall from grace, he staffed the San Francisco Conference as acting secretary-general. This man, who was thought to be the operative codenamed \u201cALES,\u201d was convicted of perjury after Richard Nixon led a HUAC investigation against him. Whittaker Chambers said that this man had hid a series of film rolls inside a gourd, the so-called Pumpkin Papers. For the point, name this former state department official who was accused of being a Soviet spy in 1948.", "answer": "Alger<b> Hiss</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This event inspired a track on the album<em> Some Time in New York City</em> that asks \u201cIs there any one among you / Dare to blame it on the kids?\u201d The release of the single \u201cMary Had a Little Lamb\u201d was interpreted as a satirical response to the banning of another song inspired by this event, which was simply called \u201ca record by Wings\u201d by BBC DJs when it reached #16 in 1972. The most commercially-successful song named for this event describes \u201cbroken bottles under children\u2019s feet\u201d and opens \u201cI can\u2019t believe the news today.\u201d Bono cries \u201cHow long? How long must we sing this song?\u201d in a song about, for the point, what mass shooting by British soldiers in Derry in Northern Ireland?", "answer": "<b> Bloody Sunday</b> (accept<b> Bogside Massacre</b> until \u201cnamed for\u201d is read; prompt on \u201cthe Troubles\u201d and descriptions of violence in (Northern) Ireland until \u201cnamed for\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This dynasty began to collapse after the rise of jiedushi military governors. Papermaking spread to the Western world when soldiers from this dynasty were captured at the Talas River. This dynasty was briefly interrupted when a competing Zhou dynasty was established by Wu Zetian. A sixth of the world\u2019s population may have died when this dynasty faced the revolt of An Lushan. For the point, name this Chinese dynasty in which the poets Du Fu and Li Po were active in the 8th century AD.", "answer": "<b> Tang</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A dreaming character in this work sees a house where people eat clay in the \u201chouse of dust\u201d of the underworld. Seven progressively staler loaves of bread indicate that the protagonist of this work failed to stay awake for seven days, preventing him from receiving the secret of immortality from Utnapishtim. This work was rediscovered in its 12-tablet form in the 19th century in excavations of the library of Ashurbanipal. A one-third mortal, two-thirds immortal Sumerian king is the namesake protagonist of, for the point, what ancient Mesopotamian epic poem?", "answer": "Epic of<b> Gilgamesh</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "Shortly after winning at Heraclea, this man won a battle where a Roman commander was flung into this man\u2019s troops to provide good luck. Maleventum was renamed Beneventum after a Roman victory over this man, who won the Battle of Asculum after being invited by Tarentum to Italy. Following a loss in Sparta, an old woman dropped a tile, killing this man. For the point, name this general from Epirus whose name now describes an overly costly victory.", "answer": "<b> Pyrrhus</b> of Epirus", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This composer had a falling out with violinist Ede Remenyi after he fell asleep during Franz Liszt\u2019s performance of a Remenyi work. Unlike Rachmaninoff\u2019s<em> Rhapsody</em>, this composer was inspired to compose a set of<em> Variations on</em> Niccolo Paganini\u2019s 24th caprice. According to legend, this man scoffed \u201cAny ass can see that!\u201d when critics compared his first symphony to Beethoven, calling it \u201cBeethoven\u2019s Tenth.\u201dFor the point, name this German Romantic composer who joins Beethoven and Bach in the traditional\u201cThree B\u2019s\u201d of classical music.", "answer": "Johannes<b> Brahms</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Ernst Forstemann deciphered arrangements of shells, dots, and bars on one of these systems that is contained in the Dresden Codex. People recuperated during<em> Wayeb\u2019</em> periods on the<em> Haab\u2019</em> type of these systems. Base 20 and Base 18 are used in the \u201cLong Count\u201d type of these systems, which was unearthed on the side of Stela C at Tres Zapotes. An apocalypse was falsely believed to occur in 2012 due to the conclusion of a 5,126 year-long cycle in, for the point, what type of system that was used by a certain Mesoamerican civilization to keep track of days?", "answer": "<b> Maya</b>n<b> calendar</b>s (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This country was invaded in Operation Countenance, a joint operation of the UK and USSR. After this country\u2019s monarchy gave away massive business concessions named for D\u2019Arcy and Reuters, the Constitutional Revolution forced it to adopt a parliament. Operation Ajax overthrew a popular Prime Minister of this country, Mohammad Mossadegh. The last monarchial ruler of this country tried to emancipate its women in the White Revolution. For the point, name this Middle Eastern country that was ruled by the Qajar and Pahlavi dynasties from Tehran.", "answer": "<b> Iran</b> (accept<b> Persia</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man was captured by John de Menteith shortly after resigning his post in favor of John Comyn. During the \u201cAction at Lanark,\u201d this man rose to infamy by murdering the sheriff William Heselrig. Though this man was forced to abdicate the title of Guardian after losing at Falkirk, this man\u2019s alliance with Andrew Moray had scored a great victory over the Earl of Surrey in 1297. For the point, name this hero of Scotland who was victorious at Stirling Bridge.", "answer": "William<b> Wallace</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man helped represent two men who had sold National Lottery tickets that were prohibited in the state of Virginia during the Cohens case. In another case, this man noted \u201cand yet there are those who love it\u201d in defense of his alma mater in<em> Dartmouth v. Woodward</em>. This man declared \u201cLiberty and union, now and forever, one and inseparable\u201d during a debate over nullification with Robert Hayne. For the point, name this Massachusetts senator, a member of the Great Triumvirate.", "answer": "Daniel<b> Webster</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A city in this state is home to the banking neighborhood of Brickell, named for the city\u2019s co-founder. David Card and George Borjas studied this state\u2019s economy, finding a rise in low-skill wages after over 125,000 immigrants came to this state in mid-1980 during the Mariel boatlift. In 1992, over $27 billion in damage was caused by Hurricane Andrew, much of which was inflicted in this state\u2019s Dade County. For the point, name this US state where tourism has fueled the economies of cities like Miami and Orlando.", "answer": "<b> Florida</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "In a work from this discipline, G.E. Moore introduced the naturalistic fallacy; that work is titled the\u201cPrincipia\u201d of this discipline. Philippa Foot introduced a popular thought experiment to this philosophical discipline involving a trolley. Baruch Spinoza\u2019s magnum opus is titled for this concept, \u201cDemonstrated in Geometrical Order.\u201d One movement in this field emphasizes the primacy of \u201cvirtues.\u201d For the point, name this field of philosophy concerned with right and wrong.", "answer": "<b> Ethics</b> (accept<b> Ethica</b>; prompt on moral philosophy or morals)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "A senator from this state names the act that gave Puerto Rico its first civilian government after the Spanish-American War, the Foraker Act. With Fred Hartley, another senator from this state introduced a 1947 bill limiting labor union activity. Mark Hanna served as a Senator from this state after helping elect William McKinley, who had earlier governed this state. For the point, name this state, the home of William Taft, James Garfield, and six other Presidents.", "answer": "<b> Ohio</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The Maramurecs [mar-a-MUR-esh] region of Romania is famed for hundreds of buildings made from this material. In Russia, the island of Kizhi is known for its churches made of this material, including one with 22 onion domes. For the point, name this material used to construct the stave churches of Norway, as well as the \u201ccarpenter gothic\u201d churches of North America.", "answer": "<b> wood</b> (or<b> timber</b>,<b> lumber</b>,<b> logs</b> etc.; accept any specific type of wood)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This leader banned slavery in his lands after reading a letter from Ayuba Diallo. This man repulsed a foreign invasion at the Battles of Gully Hole Creek and Bloody Marsh. This man, who established his colony with land purchased from the Yamacraw chief Tomochichi, sought to aid the \u201cworthy poor\u201d after chairing a committee on prison reform. Savannah was founded as a debtor\u2019s haven by, for the point, what founder of the Georgia colony?", "answer": "James<b> Oglethorpe</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man took Saoterus as his chamberlain, who was later implicated in a murder plot against this man. This man gave Tigidius Perennis much of the responsibility of running his empire before he executed him in favor of Cleander. His first act as ruler was to end the Marcomannic Wars and he was succeeded by Pertinax. He died when Narcissus strangled him in a bath after he vomited up poison given to him by his mistress Marcia. This emperor fought as a gladiator and ended the Nerva-Antonine dynasty. For the point, name this successor of Marcus Aurelius.", "answer": "Marcus Aurelius<b> Commodus</b> Antoninus Augustus (or Lucius Aelius Aurelius<b> Commodus</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Charles Nungesser and Francois Coli\u2019s \u201cWhite Bird\u201d may have met its end in Maine while attempting this action. John Alcock and Arthur Brown became the first to accomplish this feat in 1919. To incentivize a more challenging completion of this action, Raymond Orteig offered a $25,000 prize. For the point, name this action that was performed by the<em> Spirit of St. Louis</em>, as piloted by Charles Lindbergh.", "answer": "non-stop<b> fly</b>ing<b> across</b> the<b> Atlantic</b> Ocean (accept equivalent descriptions, like nonstop <b>transatlantic flight</b>) (39) This author\u2019s father, Stephen, was chosen as a delegate to the Hartford Convention. This first American to translate the<em> Divine Comedy</em> wrote a work about a man who \u201cwith muffled oar / Silently rowed to the Charlestown shore,\u201d as well as a work that includes the line \u201cWhy don\u2019t you speak for yourself, John?\u201d This man wrote about a love triangle involving Priscilla Mullins and John Alden in<em> The</em> <em>Courtship of Miles Standish</em>, and about an April 1775 event in which he coined the phrase \u201cOne if by land, two if by sea.\u201d For the point, name this American author of<em> Paul Revere\u2019s Ride</em>. ANSWER: Henry Wadsworth<b> Longfellow</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During this battle, the flagship<em> Iron Duke</em> engaged the<em> Konig</em>. One side in this battle was criticized for initiating the \u201crun to the south.\u201d Five battlecruisers were deployed by Franz Hipper to entice David Beatty\u2019s squadron into attacking to start this battle, in which the High Seas Fleet engaged John Jellicoe\u2019s Royal Navy. For the point, name this naval battle of World War I that was fought off a Danish peninsula.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Jutland</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man designed his policy in meetings with \u201cthe Eight Elders\u201d at his home. After he was accused of organizing riots during the Qingming Festival in the wake of Zhou Enlai\u2019s death, this man was stripped of his posts. This man defended his policies by noting \u201cit doesn\u2019t matter if a cat is black or white, if it catches mice it is a good cat.\u201d This politician established Special Economic Zones and opened Shanghai to foreign investment. For the point, name this Chinese leader who oversaw the country\u2019s economic growth in the 1980s.", "answer": "<b> Deng</b> Xiaoping", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A man with this surname formed SEATO as part of a \u201cPactomania\u201d strategy of forming alliances. Another man with this surname orchestrated the overthrow of Jacobo Arbenz during Operation PBSUCCESS and organized a coup d\u2019etat against Mohammad Mossadegh as head of the CIA. Dwight Eisenhower\u2019s first Secretary of State came from this family, as did the man who oversaw the Bay of Pigs invasion under John F. Kennedy. For the point, name this American political family that included Allen and John Foster.", "answer": "<b> Dulles</b> (accept John Foster<b> Dulles</b> and/or Allen<b> Dulles</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Fort Snelling was built in this state and served as an internment camp during the 1862 Dakota War, which broke out along this state\u2019s namesake river. Iron ore deposits in this state\u2019s Mesabi Range kicked off a major mining boom in the nineteenth century. Like Maine, the Webster-Ashburton Treaty clarified this state\u2019s borders, specifically by defining its Northwest Angle. For the point, name this state where Great Lakes shipping helped grow the northern city of Duluth.", "answer": "<b> Minnesota</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This monarch received the territories of Bresse and Gex in exchange for Saluzzo from Savoy as part of the Treaty of Lyon. This monarch defeated the Duke of Mayenne at Ivry during a larger war in which this man was opposed by the Duc de Guise and the Catholic League. He issued the Edict of Nantes to institute toleration for Huguenots, but converted to Catholicism to become king, declaring \u201cParis is worth a mass.\u201d For the point, name this first Bourbon king of France.", "answer": "<b> Henry IV</b> of France (accept<b> Henry of Navarre</b>; prompt on Henry)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Outside this city\u2019s Conrad Hilton hotel, protesters chanted \u201cThe whole world is watching\u201d as police beat them. A group including the Yippie leaders Jerry Rubin and Abbie Hoffman were put on trial for protesting in this city. George McGovern was supported in a speech in this city by Abraham Ribicoff, who complained of \u201cGestapo tactics\u201d during the 1968 Democratic National Convention. Mayor Richard J. Daley led, for the point, what largest city in Illinois?", "answer": "<b> Chicago</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "After viewing one painting about this event, Arthur George commissioned a more realistic version that included a mule borrowed from a peasant. The names of \u201cKarolus Magnus\u201d and \u201cHannibal\u201d appear in another depiction of this event, which shows the title figure pointing to the sky as his horse lifts its legs to continue a climb. Jacques-Louis David painted a depiction of, for the point, what military scene showing a French general crossing a snowy mountain range?", "answer": "<b> Napoleon Crossing the Alps</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "A member of this tribe became the final Confederate general to surrender in the Civil War. That man, Stand Watie, proved to be on the opposite side of the leader of these people, John Ross. The\u201cPhoenix\u201d newspaper of this tribe was founded by Samuel Worcester, whose arrest prompted a trial whose ruling was ignored by Andrew Jackson. Members of this tribe signed the Treaty of New Echota, leading to their forcible removal to Oklahoma on the Trail of Tears. For the point, name this Native American tribe whose writing system was invented by Sequoyah.", "answer": "<b> Cherokee</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This justice\u2019s opinion in the<em> Silverthorne Lumber</em> case warned against the usage of illegally obtained evidence, the first instance of the \u201cfruit from the poisonous tree\u201d doctrine. This justice declared that\u201cthree generations of imbeciles are enough\u201d in defense of forced sterilizations in<em> Buck v. Bell</em>. The \u201cclear and present danger\u201d doctrine in the case<em> Schenck v. US</em> was formulated by, for the point, what Supreme Court justice who wrote that shouting \u201cfire\u201d in a crowded theater is not protected by free speech?", "answer": "Oliver Wendell<b> Holmes</b> Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An activist from this city was invited to speak in Thailand on the 40th anniversary of the Thammasat University massacre but was detained instead. A legislator from this region used a derogatory Japanese slur for China while taking an oath of office. This city, which saw the rise of the Demosisto party, saw Yau Wai Ching lose her Kowloon West legislative council seat. Agnes Chow lost a 2018 by-election in, for the point, what island city where Joshua Wong was imprisoned during the Umbrella Movement?", "answer": "<b> Hong Kong</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man constructed the highest gateway in the world, Buland Darzawa, to commemorate victory over Gujarat. The reign of this man was chronicled by Abu Fazl and included a regency period where the kingdom was ruled by Bairam Khan. \u201cNine Jewels\u201d of this man\u2019s court included Faizi and Birbal, who aided this man in establishing a syncretic religion known as Din-i-ilahi. This man\u2019s other religious reforms included abolishing the jizya tax on non-Muslims. For the point, name this great Mughal emperor, the son of Humayun.", "answer": "<b> Akbar</b> the Great (or<b> Akbar</b> I; accept Abu\u2019l-Fath Jalal-ud-din Muhammad<b> Akbar</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This colony was founded after members of the Dorchester Company failed to fund a settlement at Cape Ann. The<em> Arbella</em> carried the first settlers to this colony, whose population swelled during the Great Migration, which brought in many Puritans. Residents of this colony were asked to be a \u201ccity upon a hill\u201das a \u201cmodel of Christian charity\u201d by founder John Winthrop. For the point, name this American colony that was centered around Boston.", "answer": "<b> Massachusetts Bay</b> Colony (prompt on Massachusetts)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The owner of Four Seasons resorts, Isadore Sharp, founded a marathon to fight this disease. Percival Pott discovered a form of this disease common to chimney sweeps, the first time it had been blamed on environmental factors. An athlete with this disease ran from St. John\u2019s, Newfoundland to Thunder Bay, Ontaro before dying in the Marathon of Hope. Terry Fox raised money for, for the point, what class of diseases that often presents with abnormal cell growth, causing tumors?", "answer": "<b> cancer</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s military reforms were the subject of the Burghal Hidage, which described how a series of defensive \u201cburhs\u201d were established. After suffering a loss at Chippenham, this man was forced to hide in the Somerset marshes while his forces recovered. This man limited the size of the Danelaw after a victory at Edington against Guthrum, a Viking invader. For the point, name this English monarch who expanded Wessex\u2019s power in the late 9th century.", "answer": "<b> Alfred the Great</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s early career included meritorious service under Edward Preble and a stint overseeing the Gosport Shipyard. After this man questioned James Barron\u2019s leadership during the Chesapeake-Leopard Affair, Barron shot and killed him in a duel. This leader won acclaim as a war hero after leading a daring night raid to burn the<em> USS Philadelphia</em>, which had previously been captured by Barbary pirates. For the point, name this distinguished naval officer, the youngest to become a captain in US history.", "answer": "Stephen<b> Decatur</b> Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s attempts to reform the Palmach special forces led to the Generals\u2019 Revolt. Racial unrest in Yemen prompted this man to launch Operation Magic Carpet, in which refugees were airlifted into his country. This man merged the Irgun and other militias into a unified defense force to fight the 1948 War of Independence, after which he led the Mapai party as the first head of state of his country. For the point, name this first Prime Minister of Israel.", "answer": "David<b> Ben-Gurion</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A composer who worked in this city wrote a characteristically short<em> Concerto for Nine Instruments</em> and evacuated this city near the end of World War II. Another composer who worked and died in this city left unfinished an opera based on Frank Wedekind\u2019s<em> Lulu</em> plays. Those composers, Anton Webern and Alban Berg, helped promote a \u201cnew school\u201d of music based in this city that popularized the twelve-tone technique invented by its founder, Arnold Schoenberg. For the point, name this city where more typically classical composers like Haydn and Mozart worked in Austria.", "answer": "<b> Vienna</b> (or<b> Wien</b>; accept Second<b> Viennese</b> School)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This battle featured Robert Toombs\u2019 valiant defense of Burnside\u2019s Bridge, where Union troops were stalled for three hours. The losing side in this battle took up defensive positions in Miller\u2019s Cornfield and Dunker Church. After winning control of a sunken road known as the \u201cBloody Lane,\u201d George McClellan was sacked for failing to follow up on his victory in this battle. For the point, name this 1862 battle in Maryland, the bloodiest single day of the Civil War.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Antietam</b> (or Battle of<b> Sharpsburg</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "These people conquered the Denkyira nation to gain access to trade with the Netherlands during the rule of Osei Tutu. Mitchell Hodgson was attacked by these people after attempting to sit on their sacred throne, the Golden Stool. Garnet Wolseley defeated these people in a series of colonial wars with Britain, leading their land to be absorbed into the Gold Coast colony. For the point, name this empire that was based in modern day Ghana.", "answer": "<b> Ashanti</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This leader constructed the Sainte-Chapelle complex to house the Crown of Thorns and parts of the True Cross, which he had purchased from the Byzantines. A heavy defeat at Fariskur ended this leader\u2019s most famous campaign, in which he captured the city of Damietta. Blanche of Castile ruled in this leader\u2019s name while he fought in the Seventh Crusade. An outbreak of dysentery eventually killed this man while he was encamped in Tunisia. For the point, name this French king who was canonized in 1297.", "answer": "<b> Louis IX</b> (accept<b> Saint Louis</b>; prompt on Louis)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The founder of this group formulated the daily \u201cexamen\u201d prayer in his book, the Spiritual Exercises. In the 1773 brief<em> Dominus ac Redemptor</em>, Clement XIV ordered the suppression of this group. Missionaries from this order created the Vietnamese alphabet and were the first to spread Catholicism to Japan as part of its 16th-century Asian mission led by Francis Xavier. Pope Francis is the first pope to be a member of this order. For the point, name this Catholic order founded by Ignatius of Loyola, known for its universities.", "answer": "<b> Jesuit</b>s (or the<b> Society of Jesus</b>; or<b> Societas Jesu</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This country was the site of Operation Dragon Rouge, where Belgian troops defeated the communist Simba rebels. Peace negotiations in this country were thwarted when Dag Hammarskjold, the UN Secretary-General, died in a plane crash. Laurent Kabila successfully led rebel troops in overthrowing this country\u2019s leader, Mobutu Sese Seko. For the point, name this country that was briefly named Zaire and has its capital at Kinshasa.", "answer": "<b> D</b>emocratic<b> R</b>epublic of the<b> C</b>ongo (accept<b> Zaire</b> before mentioned; prompt on Congo; do not accept Republic of the Congo)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man captured the city of Giurgiu [jur-joo] and executed Hamza Pasha after a dispute over the jizya tax. He was briefly imprisoned by Matthias Corvinus after entering Hungary to seek military aid. This man\u2019s \u201cNight Attack\u201d failed to capture his great enemy, Mehmed II, at Targoviste, where this man had executed 23,000 Ottomans in signature fashion. The cruelty of this ruler inspired a famous Bram Stoker novel. For the point, name this ruler of Wallachia who mounted his enemies on stakes.", "answer": "<b> Vlad the Impaler</b> (accept<b> Vlad Tepes</b> or<b> Vlad III</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This event was overseen by Otto Braun until his removal at the Zunyi Conference. During this event, the crossing of the Luding Bridge proved to be a great propaganda victory. The Encirclement Campaigns necessitated this event, whose planners were interviewed in Edgar Snow\u2019s<em> Red Star Over China</em>. For the point, name this event, a military escape to Shaanxi to save the Red Army that was led by Mao Zedong in the Chinese Civil War.", "answer": "<b> Long March</b> (or Hongjun<b> Chang Zheng</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this war, the Black Tom raid featured the detonation of an ammo dump near the Statue of Liberty. This war featured the usage of the Four Minute Men to drum up support through quick speeches. Wobblies and socialists who spoke against this war were jailed under the Sedition Act, which put Eugene Debs into jail. During this conflict, the public renamed hamburgers and sauerkraut to \u201cliberty steak\u201d and\u201cliberty cabbage.\u201d For the point, Woodrow Wilson led America through what 20th century war?", "answer": "<b> World War I</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}